Bushnell, David Ives, Jr. (1875-1941) Collection Records, 1845-1942: A Finding Aid 41-72
Peabody Museum Archives
David I. Bushnell, Jr. collection records
1845-1942
Peabody Museum Archives
Bushnell, David I. (David Ives)
Fewkes, Jesse Walter, 1850-1930
Grue, W. P.
Holmes, William Henry, 1846-1933
Lange, Otto, 1879-1944
Smithsonian Institution
41-72
2.25 linear feet
General
Collections records may contain language, reflecting past collecting practices and methods of analysis, that is no longer acceptable. The Peabody Museum is committed to addressing the problem of offensive and discriminatory language present in its database. Our museum staff are continually updating these records, adding to and improving content. We welcome your feedback and any questions or concerns you may want to share.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
David I. Bushnell bequeathed part of his ethnographic and archaeological collection to the Peabody Museum when he died in 1941. His mother, Mrs. Belle Johnston Bushnell, eventually donated his remaining collection to the Peabody Museum in 1946. The Bushnell Collection Records accompanied the large painting and artifact collection. A portion of the collection was catalogued at its accession date, and the collection was dispersed throughout the museum. In 1995 the remainder of the collection was catalogued, and photographs were transferred to Photo Archives. The records were transferred to the Archives in 1997.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in the following series, according to the Bushnell's organization and subsequent research needs: I. Correspondence - Artist Related 1917 - 1939, II. Correspondence / Multiple Artist Related 1926 - 1942, III.Correspondence/ Dealers 1922 - 1937, IV. Correspondence/ General 1918 - 1938, n.d., V. Field Notes 1899 - 1910, VI. Manuscripts and Notes 1926 - 1939, n.d., VII. Ephemera 1915 - 1951, VIII. Catalogues.
Biographical Sketch
Born in 1875 in St. Louis, Missouri, David Ives Bushnell, Jr. was introduced to archaeological and ethnographic material at an early age. His father, David Bushnell, Sr., served on the Advisory Committee at the Missouri Historical Society for many years, was appointed the vice-president at one time, and was a trustee from 1898-1913.
Never formally trained as an anthropologist, David I. Bushnell Jr. enjoyed a wide range of interests in the field of anthropology, archaeology and ethnography. Bushnell extensively photographed his numerous expeditions, many of which resulted in the publications he produced throughout his life.
Schooled in St. Louis and later in Europe, Bushnell was never a student at Harvard University, but was associated with the University from 1901-1904 as an archaeological assistant at the Peabody Museum. He was later appointed as an editor at the Smithsonian Institution's Bureau of American Ethnology (BAE) where he remained from 1912-1921. His widespread interests and his reputation as a scholar and collector began in 1899 when Bushnell embarked on his first anthropological expedition to Northern Minnesota where he observed and recorded life among the Chippewa and Ojibwa as well as participated in an archaeological excavation at Mille Lac. In 1902, he studied saltmaking at Kimmswick in southern Missouri.
In 1904, Bushnell excavated at the Cahokia Mounds. That same year, he also took a trip with his mother to Europe and documented North American ethnographic material housed in European collections and museums. While in Switzerland, he excavated and collected specimens from peat bogs. He returned to Charlottesville, Virginia in 1907 and was hired as a contributor to the Handbook of American Indians. He continued his anthropological investigations in 1908-1909 to study the Choctaw in Louisiana, and later returned to the area in 1917-1918. In the decades to follow, Bushnell devoted much of his time to excavations in Virginia, specifically in the James and Rappahannock Valleys, as well as to documenting soapstone quarries in the region.
Source: PM Photographic Archives Bushnell Collection Finding Aid
Related Materials
Related Museum Collections: Bushnell Collection 41-72; Holmes Painting 979-37; Bushnell Photograph Collection 41-72. Please see Photographic Archives Bushnell finding aid for related photos.
Scope and Contents
The papers primarily consist of Bushnell and the Bushnell estate's correspondence with dealers, artists, museum professionals and other collectors; Bushnell's fieldnotes from his work with the Choctaw and archaeological expeditions; and, manuscript drafts and notes for his many publications.
Folsom points; Mounds -- United States; Soapstone; Wampum; Clippings; Correspondence; Drawings; Field notes; Manuscripts; Maps; Notebooks; Photographs; Portraits; Postcards; Proofs; Sketches; Native American; Choctaw (culture or style); Ojibwa (culture or style); Dance; Hopi (culture or style); Indigenous peoples -- Material culture; Timucua; Artists -- United States; Five Civilized Tribes; Salt industry and trade -- Mississippi River Valley; Monacan; Indigenous peoples -- Northwest Coast of North America; Indigenous peoples -- California; Indigenous peoples -- Virginia; Indigenous peoples -- Alaska; Ephemera (general object genre); Catalogs; Songs; Storytelling; Photography Plates; Excavations (Archaeology) -- Mounds -- Forest Park (Ill.); Excavations (Archaeology) -- Mitchell Mounds (Ill.); Excavations (Archaeology) -- Mounds -- Leavell Farm Site (Va.); Choctaw language -- Glossaries, vocabularies, etc.; Ojibwa language -- Glossaries, vocabularies, etc.; Art dealers -- Correspondence; Manahoac; Ethnography -- Saint Tammany Parish (La.) -- Lacombe (La.) -- Twentieth century; Paintings -- Indigenous peoples -- United States -- Correspondence; Virginia -- Indigenous peoples -- River settlements; Wimar, Carl, 1828-1862; Pomarede, Leon, c1807-1892; Stanley, John Mix; Le Moyne de Morgues, Jacques; Catlin, George, 1796-1872; Batz, Alexandre de; Eastman, Seth; Kane, Paul; Kern, Edward Meyer; Krieghoff, Cornelius
- I. Correspondence related to individual artists, 1845-1940 (Box 1)
  - Bernard, 1921-11-01; 1.1A; 2 items
  - George Catlin, 1845-1918; August 13-27, 1918,; July 8 - August 7,1845; 1.1B; 3 items
  - A. DeBatz, 1923-1924; 1.1C; 3 items
  - Seth Eastman, including W. H. Holmes and Charles C. Curran correspondence, 1923-1937; 1.1D; 9 items
    Eastman, Seth
  - Matthew Hastings, 1922-07-27; 1.1E; 1 items
  - William Henry Holmes, 1872, undated; 1.1F; 3 items
  - William Henry Jackson, 1924-02-20; 1.1G; 1 items
  - John G. Jebb, 1937-08-27; 1.1H; 1 items
  - Paul Kane, 1926-1939; 1.1I; 8 items
    Kane, Paul
  - Edward Meyer Kern, 1938-1940; 1.1J; 15 items
    Kern, Edward Meyer
  - Cornelius Krieghoff, 1919-1924; 1.1K; 5 items
    Krieghoff, Cornelius
  - Jacques Le Moyne, 1925-1928; 1.1L; 3 items
    Le Moyne de Morgues, Jacques
  - Thomas Mower Martin, 1931-06-04; 1.1M; 1 items
  - Alfred Jacob Miller, 1924-04-09; 1.1N; 1 items
  - Hobart Nichols, undated; 1.1O; 1 items
  - Leon Pomarede, 1912-1919; 1.1P; 7 items
  - Romney, 1924-08-27; 1.1Q; 1 items
  - John Stanley, including excerpt from W. H. Emory, "Notes of a Military Reconnaissance," Congressional Record, 30th Congress, 1st Session, 1848, 1924-1927; 1.1R; 5 items
    Stanley, John Mix
  - Benjamin West, 1937-02-17; 1.1S; 1 items
  - Charles Whymper, 1922-10-24; 1.1T; 1 items
    Whymper, Charles
  - Carl Wimar, 1920-1921; 1.1U; 3 items
- II. Correspondence regarding multiple artists, 1926-1942 (Box 1)
  - Louis Choris, John Webber, George Caitlin, Paul Kane, George Back, William Smyth, Charles Whymper, George Gibbs and Henry Wood Elliott, 1926-1942; 1.2A; 5 items
    Kane, Paul; Whymper, Charles
- III. Correspondence with dealers, 1922-1937 (Box 1)
  - Otto Lange; H. W. Bromhead regarding portrait by Francis Parsons; Walter C. Wyman regarding Mr. Temple and Charles Bird King; W. Davidson, 1922-1937; 1.3; 6 items
- IV. Correspondence, general and archaeology, 1839-1938 (Box 1)
  - Kaj Birket-Smith to M. W. Stirling regarding early Eskimo pictures; Capt. H. Day, "Memo. for Capt. Barker," with map of portion of Suwanee [sic] River on verso; Benjamin Rand to John R. Swanton regarding painting of "Georgia Trustees"; De Cost Smith regarding robe in Berne Museum; I. C. Sutton to J. Walter Fewkes regarding 1692 manuscript by Lindestrom, 1839-1937; 1.4A; 9 items
  - Sites and artifacts including soapstone dipper, Leavell Farm Mound, VA, Paynes Quarry, soapstone quarry in Bristol, artifacts for World's Fair and article on "Folsom type" points, 1892-1938; 1.4B; 8 Sheets
  - Cahokia Group Mounds - J. Walter Fewkes; G. D. L.; W. P. Grue; Frank M. Kennedy; H. Munroe; Harold R. Wells, 1921-1922; 1.4C; 16 items
- V. Field notes (numbers shown are PM artifact catalogue numbers), 1899-1908; 1.5 (Box 1)
  - Ojibway dootem (totem) drawings by their "owners" (on cards), collected by Frances Densmore, 1907-1908; 1.5A
  - Field Book No. 1, "Indian Note Book" Folio 46-5B, 1899-09-17-1900-11-27; 1.5B
    General
    The material collected in this notebook was used by Mr. Bushnell in Ojibway Habitation and Other Structures, Annual Report of the Smithsonian Institution, 1917." (See Photo Archives for photographs.) Includes trip log, weather notes, expedition members and guide names, vocabularies, maps of mound sites (Forest Park in St. Louis and Mitchell Mounds, Madison Co., IL), descriptions and drawings of artifacts from Larchmont, NY. 41-72/314b
  - Field Book No. 2, 1900-11-27-1902-09-14; 1.5C
    Includes field notes, maps, and sketches related to sites in Illinois and Missouri, including Cahokia Mounds (Acc. No. 01- 16). See Photo Archives for related photos. 41-72/314d
  - Book 1, "The Choctaw of Bayou Lacombe Louisiana", 1909; 1.5D
    Includes general observations, vocabulary lists, song transcriptions, dance descriptions, and photographs, of Choctaws living in St. Tammany parish, Jan. and Feb. 1909.
  - Book 3, "Myths and Legends of the Chocktaw of Bayou Lacombe, Louisiana", 1909; 1.5E
  - "Songs and Myths of the Choctaw," New Orleans, 1910; 1.5F
  - Specimens from the Kircheriano Museum, Rome; and Sketches from Swiss museums and private collections, 1904-1905; 5.1
  - Fieldnotes and sketches, 1905
- VI. Manuscripts and notes, 1849-1939 (Box 2, Box 3, Box 4)
  - Notes on archaeological artifacts, undated; 2.1
    From various locations, mainly artifacts in the U.S. National Museum. Includes photographs of artifacts [mostly soapstone vessels], n.d.
  - "Drawings and Paintings of Indians and Eskimo of North America North of Mexico, A Chronological Record"; "Catalogue of Indian Paintings Belonging to the Government Collection" (Smithsonian), 1924-1937; 2.2; 8pp. on lined paper.
    "North America" catalogue notebook III contains the following typescript manscript sections: "Introduction," "Early contact with Native Tribes, 16th Century," "Jacques LeMoyne de Morgues," "Portrait of an Eskimo, 1576," "John White," and "Pocahontas, Booton Hall Portrait - 1616;"
  - A. DeBatz, drawings, Louisiana, undated; 2.3; 4 photographs of drawings / paintings.
    with typed descriptions, for publication in Smithsonian Misc. Coll. 80 (5) monograph series. With reprint (paintings nos. 17-20), 1927.
  - "Drawings by George Gibbs in the Far Northwest", 1849-1851; 2.4
    Typescript manuscript.copy, n.d. Published in Smithsonian Misc. Coll. 97(8).
  - Drawings for/from unidentified publications, [1871?] undated; 2.5
    - Mounted inked map of northern Virginia, including a portion of the Potomac River, undated; 2.5A
      [in oversize box]
    - "Moqui [woman] dressed for a dance" pencil sketch, undated; 2.5B
      Title is the original transcribed directly from the material.
    - A.Z. Schindler, Blackmore Expedition, print from painting, 1871; 2.5C
    - Plate, "Inscriptio lateri perpendiculari Rupis in fluvio Taunton Nova Anglico insculpta", undated; 2.5D
    - Pen and ink sketch of person in headdress, undated; 2.5E
    - Pen and ink sketch, undated; 2.5F
    - Pen and ink sketch of unidentified shell heap, undated; 2.5G
  - E. de Girardin, photographs of drawings, with some references and quotations, 41-72/761, undated; 2.6
  - Eastman, notebook on plates in Schoolcraft publication., undated; 2.7
    With note cards re: paintings, n.d. 41-72/762
  - B. DeVoto, The First Painters of the Far West, undated; 2.8
    41-72/768
  - The Five Monacan Towns in Virginia, c. 1930; 2.9
    Published in Smithsonian Misc. Coll., 1930.
  - Gibbs-related material: Copies of excerpts from four U.S. Senate documents regarding Northwest Coast groups, undated; 2.10
    41-72/264a
  - "Indian Occupancy between the James and Rivanna Rivers in Virginia", undated; 2.11; Carbon typescript.; 31pp.
  - "Indian Sites on the Rappahannock", undated; 2.12; Paste-ups for plates.
    See PM Photo Archives for photographic plates.
  - Edward M. Kern, 1937, undated; 2.13
    Manuscript material which includes transcriptions, excerpts from unpublished works, description of Kuksuy Dance, excerpts from Congressional Register, re: Kerns and California Indians. Some multiple copies. 41-72/763
  - The Manahoac Tribes in Virginia, 1608, circa 1935; 2.14; Carbon typescript of text sent to printer, with plate paste-ups July 8, 1935.
  - "Morris/Kane" notebook: notes relating to Paul Kane, undated; 3.1
    41-72/766
  - Notes on artists, undated; 3.2
    Packet of sheets with birth/ death dates and places for 29 artists, with some notes.
  - Herman Ten Kate, On Paintings of North American Indians and Their Ethnographical Value, undated; 3.3; Typescript manuscript, n.d. Annotated by W. H. Holmes, "written but not printed."
    Published in Anthropos, VI, pp. 523-545. 41-72/767
  - "Paul Kane:His Wanderings and His Art", undated; 3.4; Typescript manuscript with illustrations and plates lists.
  - "Rappahannock below the Falls", undated; 3.5; Typescript manuscript of "Indian Sites on the Rappahannock," n.d.
    Smithsonian Misc. Coll. 96(4), ca. 1937.
  - "Salt among Native Tribes of the Mississippi Valley and Eastward", undated; 3.6; Typescript manuscript., n.d.
    Annotated " L.SOC 120.1" [Tozzer Library catalogue number], ns., vol. 44, p. 104, published in American Anthropologist?
  - Sketches by Paul Kane in the Indian Country, 1845-1848, 3.7
    2 reprints with holograph notes, n.d. Smithsonian Misc. Coll. 99(1): incl. plates list and list of paintings.
  - "Sketches by Paul Kane in the Indian Country, 1845-1848", 1938-09-19; 3.8; Typescript manuscript.
    Published in Smithsonian Misc. Coll. 99(1). With reprint of same.
  - "The Use of Soapstone by the Indians of Eastern United States", 1939-04-18; 3.9; Typescript manuscript.
    With: Notes, photographs, and figures, n.d. Related to Virginia soapstone quarries for the above publication and: "Ancient Soapstone Quarry in Abemarle County, Virginia," Journal of the Washington Academy of Science 16(19), 1926.
    Published as "The Use of Soapstone by the Indians of Eastern United States," Smithsonian Annual Report for 1939.
  - Notebook: Notes relating to Frederick Arthur Verner, 1836-1928, and his Indian pictures, Toronto, 1931; 4.1
    Includes both biographical notes on Verner and notes on his painting, "Ojibwa Indians Shooting the Rapids." 41-72/765
- VII. Ephemera, 1905-1946 (Box 4)
  - Membership in professonal societies, 1905-1915; 4.2
  - Miscellaneous printed materials, undated; 4.3
    - Reproduction of engraving, Comandante Principale / Principal Commandant, undated; 4.3A
    - Mission Dolores, postcards and pamphlet, undated; 4.3B
    - Photographic plate of Edward Burnett Tylor, Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute v. 38, 1907; 4.3C
  - Ad for Virginia Historical Index, with proofs of index to same publication pp. 988-1005, undated; 4.4
  - Reprints, 4.5
    - Drawings by George Gibbs in the far Northwest, 1849 - 1851. Washington, DC: Smithsonian Institution, 1938-12-30; 4.5A
    - Drawing by Jacques LeMoyne de Morgues of Saturoua: A Timuca Chief in Florida,1564. Washington, DC: Smithsonian Institution, 1928-08-03; 4.5B
    - Drawings by John Webber of Natives of the Northwest Coast of America, 1778. Washington, DC: Smithsonian Institution, 1928-03-24; 4.5C
    - Seth Eastman: The Master Painter of the North American Indian. Washington, DC: Smithsonian Institution, 1932-04-11; 4.5D
    - Perry T. Rathbone, Charles Wimar 1828 - 1862: Painter of the Indian Frontier. St. Louis, MO: City Art Museum of St. Louis., 1946; 4.5E
    - Obituary for W. H. Holmes, Science, vol. 77, no. 2000, 1933; 4.5F
- VIII. Catalogues, 1925, undated (Box 5)
  - Paintings and Drawings of Indians and Eskimo North of Mexico, 1925; 5.1-2
  - G. Verona Taylor Whatmough, The Bushnell Collection of Paintings and Other Works by Early American Artists", undated; 5.3-4
- Oversize Materials (Box 6)
eyJtZXRhZGF0YV9wcmVmaXgiOiJvYWlfZWFkIiwiZnJvbSI6IjIwMjMtMDQtMTMgMDA6MDA6MDAgVVRDIiwidW50aWwiOiIyMDIzLTA0LTE0IDA3OjAwOjA0IFVUQyIsInN0YXRlIjoicHJvZHVjaW5nX3JlY29yZHMiLCJsYXN0X2RlbGV0ZV9pZCI6MCwicmVtYWluaW5nX3R5cGVzIjp7IlJlc291cmNlIjo0NzQxfSwiaXNzdWVfdGltZSI6MTY4MTQ3OTY0NTMzMX0=